Okay so today's דף Daf is
למד ב עמוד ב, Lamed Bais Amud Bais, actually we start on
למד ב עמוד ב Lamed Bais Amud Bais but the דף Daf
is
למד ג. Lamed Gimmel. Okay, whatever. Anyway so we pick up here
where the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אמר רבי חלבו, Amar Rabbi Chelbo, אנא חזיתיה. Ana Chazeisay. So start
with the word חזיתיה, Chazeisay, right there is like an asterisk in
the middle of the long line, there is a little גמל Gimmel
in רש״י Rashi letters and a half square column about twenty lines
down. The line starts with חזיתיה. Chazeisay. Okay so אמר רבי חלבו,
Amar Rabbi Chelbo, אנא חזיתיה לרב הונא, Ana Chazeisay l'Rav Huna, דהוה
יתיב אפוריא דספר תורה עלה. D'hava yasiv a puraya d'Sefer Torah ala.
He was sitting on a bed that there was a ספר תורה
Sefer Torah on it. כפה כדא אארעא. Kafa kada a-ara. So what
he did was he upturned a barrel, or not a barrel, like
whatever, like some kind of pitcher. It's a, what do you call
those? A jug. A jug, thank you, on the ground. ואנח עליה
ספר תורה. V'anach lei Sefer Torah. And then so he took the
ספר תורה Sefer Torah off the bed, he put it on this
now upturned
jug. והדר יתיב בניתא. V'hadar yasiv b'nisa. And then he was willing
to sit on the bed. That makes sense. קסבר, Kasavar, he is
of the opinion, אסור לישב על גבי מטה שספר תורה מונח עליה.
Asur leishev agabei mita sheSefer Torah munach aleha. Forbidden to sit on
a bed that a ספר תורה Sefer Torah is on there. So
there you go David, we have at least an interpretation of some
distinct status of a ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. We don't say this
by other ספרים, Sfarim, we say it by a ספר תורה. Sefer
Torah. Isn't it on קלף? Klaf? Right there is, correct, so it's
not just a direct function of its קדושה, Kedusha, you know כסא
הקדש, Kissei Hakodesh, so specifically
I don't think...
But it was on the bed.
But it was on the bed,
someone left it.
Okay, they didn't have too many cabinets or whatever around. That's true,
but you can't sit on it when it's there. Okay, ופליגי דרבה
בר בר חנה. U'pligi d'Rabba bar bar Chana. And this argues on
רבה בר בר חנה. Rabba bar bar Chana. דאמר רבה בר בר
חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, Damar Rabba bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan,
מותר לישב על גבי מטה שספר תורה מונח עליה. Mutar leishev agabei
mita sheSefer Torah munach aleha. You're allowed to sit on a bed
that there is a ספר תורה Sefer Torah is on it. ואם
לחשך אדם לומר, V'im lachashacha adam lomar, if somebody whispers to you
and says to you how could you say such a thing, don't
you know about the famous story of מעשה ברבי אליעזר שהיה יושב
על המטה, Maaseh b'Rabbi Eliezer shehaya yoshev al hamita, he was sitting
on a bed, רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, ונזכר שספר תורה מונח עליה,
V'nizkar sheSefer Torah munach aleha, and he realized that there was a
ספר תורה Sefer Torah on the bed. ונשמט וישב על גבי קרקע,
V'nishmat v'yashav agabei karka, he slipped off the bed and he sat
on the ground. So obviously how could you think that it's מותר
Mutar to sit on a bed that there's a ספר תורה Sefer
Torah on it? So the גמרא Gemara says no, ודומה כמי שהכישו
נחש, V'domeh k'mi shehiki'o nachash, and he reacted as like a snake
had bitten him, he was so shocked that he jumped off the
bed and went to the ground. The גמרא Gemara says, yeah you
got the story wrong. התם ספר תורה על גבי קרקע הוה. Hatam
Sefer Torah agabei karka hava. It wasn't that he reacted because the
ספר תורה Sefer Torah was on the bed, he reacted because he
was sitting on a bed and he realized somebody had left the
ספר תורה Sefer Torah on the ground. So he jumped off the
bed and he went to the ground, I don't know, maybe presumably
then he took the ספר תורה Sefer Torah and put it on
the bed. Doesn't quite explain why he didn't stay on the bed
and then move the ספר תורה Sefer Torah there, but okay, somehow
we got the actual story a little bit incorrect. So here you
have without any sort of broader framework this debate or this statement
that you cannot have, be sitting on a bed with a ספר
תורה, Sefer Torah, which again gets to these issues about the status
of כסא הקדש. Kissei Hakodesh. There are other discussions that are more
elaborate about that, about putting, you know,
נביאים Neviim on top of תורה, Torah, and כתובים Kesuvim on top
of נביאים Neviim and how you sort of order them and stack
them and so on. An interesting question comes up nowadays about the
whole status of our printed books. If you walk into some of
these crowded ספרים Sfarim stores where they have some of their books
actually on the ground itself, if you look close most of them
will have like a piece of cardboard, right, so it's not actually
directly on the ground. To make it better? So well, you know,
it's sort of like you're not directly sitting on the... You're standing
on the exact same surface as the... Real question is whether it's
an issue altogether, whether our printed ספרים Sfarim have the קדושה Kedusha
of ספרים Sfarim that's being referred to. Anyway, here we aren't just
talking, probably not. Here we aren't just talking about קדושת ספרים Kedushas
Sfarim generically, we're talking specifically about קדושת ספר תורה. Kedushas Sefer Torah.
And we're saying though that it does make a difference if it
was actually written by a סופר Sofer on a קלף, Klaf, meaning
like we do...
Yeah I mean we aren't having this discussion, but that's the assumption,
that's specific to ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. What if it would try
the same be true about חומשים? Chumashim?
You know what I mean? It's close to תפילין Tefillin and מזוזות.
Mezuzos. Oh, so let's say there were תפילין Tefillin on the bed.
You know, nowadays of course we'd know it all equally, but the
גמרא, Gemara, I have to check, this גמרא Gemara specifically is relating
to the unique status of its own, but what is a little
frustrating is it's not putting it in a larger context. It's not
doing exactly that, looking at how to relate to תפילין Tefillin or
מזוזות, Mezuzos, how does it fit into other aspects of קדושת ספר
תורה? Kedushas Sefer Torah?
And also was it just the scroll or was it actually in
something? Maybe it would make a difference.
Right, these are discussed elsewhere in the גמרא Gemara and certainly in
the ראשונים Rishonim and the פוסקים, Poskim, but not here. Okay, now
we turn our focus, okay, so until now we've been talking about
a lot of sort of, you know, generic but sort of a
random mix of things relating to how כסא הקדש Kissei Hakodesh are
written, sometimes talking about ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, sometimes מזוזה. Mezuza. Now
we really turn our focus a lot to מזוזה Mezuza per se,
which was the focus at least the line of the משנה Mishna
about the two פרשיות Parshiyos in the מזוזה. Mezuza. Now we talk
both about where the מזוזה Mezuza is, not just how the scroll
is written, but also where it is affixed. So let's take a
look. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, so רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda said in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, כתבה, Katva,
if you wrote it,
now what's the
it referring to here? רש״י Rashi does suppose this to mean the
מזוזה. Mezuza. If you wrote it איגרת Igeret like a letter, it's
פסולה, Psula, it's invalid. What An idea of book and not אגרת
igeret and are we learning it out from סוטה? Sotah? Is it
כתב זאת זכרון בספר ksav zot zikaron basefer by עמלק? Amalek? We
see in יהושע. Yehoshua. Is it ספר כריתות, Sefer Kerisus, Rivka, the
whole question about is it are we learning the idea of certain
requirements by גט get about how things are written? The other question
is what does אגרת igeret mean? Why is אגרת igeret invalid? So
in other places אגרת, igeret, the sense was like very narrow columns,
apparently they would write narrow columns by an אגרת. igeret.
Do you remember
we said before by a מזוזה mezuzah that it was even two
words to a line was acceptable. So רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosfos
say here that אגרת igeret means either without scoring, without שרטוט, sirtut,
which we discussed before. Or it could also mean that it's like
lack of precision. Meaning if you write a letter, you don't worry
always exactly the way things are spelled, especially with human, well certainly
nowadays when we have spellcheck and whatnot. But anyway, especially if you
live in a, you know, if your language is something where there's
spelling variants, you're not going to be overly precise in exactly the
spelling. So the point here at least is that you wrote the
מזוזה, mezuzah, but you did not write the exact spelling of the
words. You know, with an acceptable variant, but it's not the way
it's written in the תורה. Torah. So here saying it's פסולה, psulah,
that degree of imprecision is invalid. And somehow we make a גזירה
שוה. gezeirah shavah. It's not clear where the גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah
is learned from and why we know the other source any better
than we know this source. But nevertheless, it's a very vague גמרא.
Gemara. Where are we learning from? What are we exactly saying? Nobody
really knows.
I mean, they don't even say what word we're talking about.
Right. They're saying we're talking about מזוזה. mezuzah. Right. A minute ago
we were talking about ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. Right, exactly.
But didn't say the word ספר sefer by מזוזה mezuzah either.
So it does not say the word ספר sefer by מזוזה, mezuzah,
that's why you need a גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah.
To what? Is it גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah because it says something
by this?
No, here it
says וכתבתם על מזוזות ביתך, uksavtem al mezuzot beitecha, somebody else says
like וכתב לה ספר כריתות vekasav lah sefer kerisut for example. And
therefore we learn that you have to write it as a ספר
sefer and not as an אגרת. igeret. But what does a ספר
sefer mean? So again, רש״י Rashi tells us it means well with
scoring, precision of how it's written. By the way, Rivka, תוספות Tosfos
says here it cannot be talking about learning it from a גט
get because if the point were to touch need שרטוט, sirtut, we've
never found that you need שרטוט sirtut by a גט. get.
But I know. I always, I know that.
I'm responding to what you said the other day.
There is no גמרא Gemara that says you need שרטוט sirtut by
a גט. get. But it doesn't mean the number of the width
of the line though, you're saying.
It could not mean because גמרא Gemara said before even if it's
two words to a line, it's okay. Alright. Now we talk about
how exactly where the מזוזה mezuzah is placed. ואמר רב יהודה אמר
שמואל. Veamar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel. So רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says
now in the, oops, it's
not going to be any good Jeff, there's no other page there.
ואמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Veamar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel, רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, תלאה במקל פסולה. telaah
bemakel psulah. If you suspend your מזוזה mezuzah on a stick, it's
invalid. Presumably people went around with their portable מזוזות, mezuzot, and they
had a מזוזה mezuzah on a stick and it was, you know,
maybe with a fixed, nailed in or something like that. And then
when they went somewhere that they didn't have a מזוזה, mezuzah, they
just stuck their stick by the door.
So that was their portable מזוזה. mezuzah. So that's invalid. It had
to be attached to the door, can't be attached to a stick.
מאי טעמא, Mai taama, what's the reason? בשעריך בעינן. Bisharecha bainan. It
has to be in your gate, not like alongside. So it had
to actually be affixed to the
doorpost itself.
Like we wear מזוזות mezuzot in chains around the neck.
used to, go down right now to Mid-Town, you see it, all
these Israeli stores, they, whatever, you know, people still do it a
lot. Like a necklace. Right. Anyway, alright. So it has to be,
it has to be
affixed in the door frame. It cannot be near the door frame.
So it needs it can't actually be a bit of an effort.
It really needs in it. It can't be like on, like we
do.
Yeah, we assume that's okay. Whether the גמרא Gemara had it that
way is right. No, no.
Alright.
תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we
taught similarly, תלאה במקל, telaah bemakel, if you suspended it from a
stick, או שהניחה אחר הדלת, o shehenichah achar hadelet, or you put
it behind the wall, behind the door. סכנה ואין בה מצוה. Sakanah
veein bah mitzvah.
It is danger and there is no מצוה. mitzvah. Now what does
danger mean? What does that mean? So רש״י Rashi says, so first
of all, I'll discuss behind the door in a minute. Anyway, רש״י
Rashi says it's danger because once it's not doing the מצוה, mitzvah,
it doesn't serve as to protect the house either, which of course
is not a reading that I prefer, but you know, we're going
to see that in a minute in the גמרא Gemara anyway that
the idea in which this מזוזה mezuzah served of a type of
a, you know, charm to protect the house and that that was
even seen as a concern even in the גמרא. Gemara. I must
say is a little troubling. Often those types of more superstitious non-halachic
attitudes you get
outside of the גמרא, Gemara, maybe contemporaneous, but not in the גמרא
Gemara itself. The גמרא Gemara tends to be very halachic and reject
those types of concerns. There will be a מדרש midrash in a
moment about how God protects us in the house. But still the
sense that it's working almost at the charm level is a little
different than the idea of God protects us. I know. So רש״י
Rashi says the סכנה sakanah is, that's what I'm saying, רש״י Rashi
reads the גמרא Gemara that way, that it is exposing us to
this danger. תוספות Tosfos says no, the סכנה sakanah is if you've
got
exactly it's going to fall on you if your doorpost you're going
to bang into it and that's your סכנה.
sakanah. So I much prefer תוספות's Tosfos reason. What is a חורי
הדלת? churei hadelet? חורי הדלת churei hadelet means that if you try
to, anyway, if this is like your door, right, and here how
it opens, and normally your מזוזה mezuzah would be, well wherever, let's
say I don't know, it opens there your מזוזה mezuzah would be...
here, it's hard to demonstrate, oh God, God, God.
If you bang the, it's better put it here. Apparently could it
like here? That would be like the חורי הדלת, chorei hadelet, right?
You're behind the door, you're not in the door, you're behind the
door.
That סכנה sakana is not clear, unless it was some sticking out
case and then when you turn the corner you could bang your
head into it.
There might be some concern. But anyway, that's how תוספות Tosafot reads
it, that
the concern is about the physical placement and it is not a
superstitious or whatever it is. What did you say?
And the מזוזה mezuzah is for protection and I was
looking
at. Right, right.
Well, that would be the case about the והמכה. vehamakah. I should
say, you know, I find it very troubling even nowadays where how
much people, you know, this is their way of thinking about מזוזה.
mezuzah. I remember once I was at somebody's house, a very modern
person, whatever, you know, somebody from this community, whatever, and they were
in a complex of houses which had, like a gate. Before, it
was one of those private roads, a little bit north of here,
where you know, you go in through, and there's like an actual
gate, and then there's like, you know, about six or eight houses
in a court sort of surrounding it. So most of the houses
in that area were, you know, were owned by Jews, so I
sat, I said, you know, I think that gate needs a מזוזה.
mezuzah. I mean, there you go, בשעריך. besharecha. So, you know, she
wasn't sure, this and that. She asked somebody else who said, 'Yeah,
I spoke to Rabbi so-and-so, he said I should put up a
מזוזה. mezuzah. Well, you know, at least it'll protect us.'
So I was like, what? That wasn't my point! You know? So
I was like, it needs a מזוזה. mezuzah.
But like this attitude, like, 'Oh, it couldn't hurt, it's gonna protect
us somewhat
from demons,' and they just assume that it's a parallel to מצרים.
Mitzrayim.
Oh, well, I do think that is a good point. You know,
that is true, if you want to look at, especially given the
time of year we're at, you know, the sense about something on
the מזוזה mezuzah to protect against the evil that's out there, that
really only occurs one place, which is by the whole case about
the מכת בכורות. makat bechorot. But nevertheless, that's not about the writing
on the מזוזה, mezuzah, but it is a sense of on your
door, the entrance to your house, your house is being protected and
so on. Now, of course, רמב״ם, Rambam, being the rationalist, says, no,
the protection comes because since every time you go in and leave
your house, you think about God and you think about what's in
the מזוזה, mezuzah, so therefore, you know, that sort of re-frames your
whole way of thinking and if there's some sense of God protecting,
it's strictly because of your thinking more about God, not because you
have this sort of charm that's protecting you. But yes, the whole
פסח Pesach story does probably evoke that. Alright, so anyway, let's take
a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: של בית מונבז המלך, shel
beit Munbaz hamalech, and the king Munbaz, they had his royal retinue,
this Jewish king, היו עושים
בפונדקאותיהן, hayu osim befundekaoteihen,
they were putting מזוזות mezuzos in their inns where they would stay,
even though they're not obligated in מזוזה, mezuzah, they were only, you
know, it's an army troop that's passing by and you know, they
don't own the space, they're not renting it long term. Nevertheless, they
would put it there זכר למזוזה. zecher lemezuzah. As to remember, you
know, they shouldn't be living in an inn and not have a
מזוזה. mezuzah. Obviously, we have that practice as well, you know, a
בית מדרש beis medrash and a בית כנסת beis knesses doesn't need
a מזוזה, mezuzah, it's not a place where people live and sleep
and actually a domicile. Nevertheless, we do it as a type of
a זכר. zecher. But again, what is nice about the גמרא, Gemara,
bracketing the רש״י Rashi before about the סכנה, sakana, is they didn't
say that they had a מזוזה mezuzah they affixed to their inn
because of סכנה. sakana. They said they affixed זכר למזוזה, zecher lemezuzah,
so it's much more from this הלכה מצוה halacha mitzvah context and
not this סכנה sakana context. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this: ואמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, ve’amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, Rav
Yehuda said in the name of Shmuel, מצוה להניחה בתוך חללו של
פתח. mitzvah lehaniacha betoch chalalo shel petach. The מצוה mitzvah is to
put it within the sort of
space of the door, not on the, not like I showed, the
back of the door or the front of the door, but within
the actual door frame itself. So the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא, peshita,
obviously, בשעריך אמר רחמנא, besharecha amar Rachmana, in your gates, the Torah
said. No, מהו דתימא, mahu deteima, I would have thought, הואיל ואמר
רבא, ho’il ve’amar Rava, since Rava said מצוה להניחה בטפח הסמוך לרשות
הרבים, mitzvah lehaniacha betefach hasamuch lereshut harabim, that the idea is to
put it in your door frame in the טפח tefach closest to
the רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, because there's thickness to your door frame,
so do you put it in the thickness more inner or more
outer? So Rava said you put it in the thickness more towards
the outside of the door.
כמאן דמרחק מעלי, keman demarchak ma'ali, so I might think the further
more on the outside the better. So maybe if you didn't even
put it in the door frame itself, but in the face of
the door frame, like where I was before, but imagine that was
the, that this was not the inside of the room but the
outside, the רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, to, it wasn't in the frame
itself, but actually on the face of the frame facing the outside,
maybe that's even better. קא משמע לן ka mashma lan that that's
not, that it had to be בשעריך, besharecha,
inside the door frame and not on the outside of the door
frame. Okay,
so where were we? So now the גמרא Gemara says like this:
ואמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, ve'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, כתבה על
שני דפין, ketavah al shenei dapin, if you wrote it on two
parchments. Now the question here is what does the word דפין dapin
mean? If you remember before when we were talking about a ספר
תורה, sefer Torah, דף daf meant a column. Here, it presumably means
two parchments. In the end, it's a question how to read the.
the גמרא Gemara but in the end everybody's going to agree that
the upshot is you can't have it on two separate little pieces
of parchment. The whole שמע והיה אם שמוע Shema v'Haya Im Shamoa
has to be on the same parchment. Okay, but let's sort of
read this now. Let's read this now maybe two columns. If you
put it on two columns it is פסולה, psula, it's invalid. So
גמרא Gemara says מיתיבי, meitivei, we have a ברייתא braita that says:
כתב על שני דפין, katav al shenei dapin, if you put it
on two columns, והניחה בשני סיפים, vehniha bishnei sipim, and you put
it in two separate, you know,
doorposts or you know maybe in the same doorframe but maybe there
were two doorposts so you separated them, you actually cut it into
two little קלפים klafim and you put it into two separate doorposts,
פסולה, psula, that's invalid. הא בסף אחד, ha besaf echad, but if
you put it into one doorpost, כשרה, keshera, it is valid. So
the גמרא Gemara says: לא, ראויה לשני סיפים קאמר. lo, re'uya lishnei
sipim ka'amar. When he said that it's
invalid if it's in two doorposts, it doesn't have to literally be
in two doorposts, it had to be fit to put it into
two doorposts. How could you have something that in theory could be
put into two doorposts? What you did is you cut it in
half. You have two little separate pieces of קלף. klaf. So what
it's saying is it's exactly the same. When I said שני דפין
shenei dapin is invalid, I did not mean two columns, I meant
two pieces of parchment. You can't have a שמע והיה אם שמוע
Shema v'Haya Im Shamoa and stick them both in. So that's not
valid. And when this said that if you put it in two
doorposts it's invalid, it didn't literally mean two doorposts, it meant fit
to be in two doorposts, not two columns on one piece of
parchment but two physically separate pieces of parchment. Okay? So the מזוזה
mezuza has to be written on one whole piece of parchment. But
it shows raised questions about the earlier גמרא Gemara we discussed about
taking from the ספר תורה Sefer Torah and using the piece of
the ספר תורה Sefer Torah for the מזוזה. mezuza. How would you
do it if you can't have separate pieces of parchment? Could you
cut them and sew them together or is that also invalid? Again,
it probably the earlier גמרא Gemara was assuming you were taking a
much larger section of the תורה Torah from the שמע Shema in
ואתחנן Va'etchanan to the והיה אם שמוע v'Haya Im Shamoa in עקב
Eikev and took all of that. But here the גמרא Gemara is
saying that it has to all be on one piece of parchment.
Okay, and now the גמרא Gemara starts talking about where in the
door you put it. I mean, we've already been talking about that,
in the doorway, not in front of the door, not on a
stick. So let's take a look.
So
the גמרא Gemara says like this. ואמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, v'amar
Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, במזוזה הלך אחר
הכר ציר. b'mezuza halech achar heker tzir.
When it comes to מזוזה, mezuza,
go by where the הכר ציר heker tzir is. What do you
call that? The hinges. Go by where the door hinge is. What
does that mean go by where the door hinge is? מאי הכר
ציר? mai heker tzir? הכר heker literally means like where it's indicated,
but the ציר tzir is the hinge. אמר רב אדא אפתא. amar
Rav Adda afta. It's the אפתא, afta, which is very helpful, which
basically means it's the hole in which you would put the hinge
of the door. What does this mean? So רש"י Rashi says because
you have to sometimes determine as we know you put a מזוזה
mezuza on the right-hand side of the way in which you enter
in. But sometimes there's a question, which way are you entering? Which
is the entranceway? Right? If it's the basic outside and inside of
the house, it's very clear which is the, which way you know,
which is the primary way you go into the house. But if
it's a basic door that faced the outside. But let's say it's
an inner room. Now I should actually say we're going to see
a little bit more about inner rooms.
You know, in the time of the גמרא, Gemara, they did not,
it was not so common that they had multi-room houses, meaning very
often a בית bayis really means a room and a room in
a house and that you know basically the whole family lived in
you know one room. So there is some question about whether you
know what we sort of take for granted,
which is clearly how we פוסקין, pasken, which is that every single
separate room requires a
מזוזה, mezuza, you know, it's not a hundred percent clear in the
גמרא. Gemara. I mean the תורה Torah says you know על מזוזות
ביתך ובשעריך. al mezuzos beitecha uvisharecha. So you could say מזוזות ביתך
mezuzos beitecha means all the מזוזות mezuzos in your house, not just
that are for the house itself. But there is a, some question
about that and actually one ראשון Rishon who believed that you did
not need it on all of the individual rooms. We clearly פוסקין
pasken that it does and there are going to be גמרות Gemaras
here that are talking about individual rooms. But again whether the context
was exactly the same as ours is not exactly clear. Anyway, the
question is let's say you have a hard time determining within between
two rooms of a house whether which way is the normal way
you enter or exit. So it says you go by where the
door hinge is. The assumption is that the door hinges is always
on the inside, not on the outside.
Is that correct David, generally speaking? I mean you don't want the
door hinge exposed on the outside because it'll let people break into
the door, right? So anyway, if the door hinge is always on
the inside so you assume that the normal way of entering is
from the face of the door where there is not the door
hinge to the side of the room where there is the door
hinge and therefore it would be on the right-hand side going from
that direction. So that's what this גמרא Gemara means to determine which
is the basic way of moving from room to room and where
you put the right, where what is the right-hand side. It's pretty
funny though of course the גמרא Gemara has never even mentioned the
issue about right hand and it's already assuming that in the background.
Yeah, but I don't think that's right. I think that normally today
to think about it, we have the handle on the right-hand side
of the door as you're going in.
A bit on the left so you would say that the handle
is on left would indicate that wait hold on the handle is
on the left.
Think about the door to your apartment. I think the handle is
on the right. Yeah. The handle's on the right. The hinge is
on the left.
The hinge is on the left. But here's now the question of
hinge left or right? My question the hinge here is into- the
hinge
is not left or right question. The hinge question is inside outside
so they're not exposed.
Right? If the hinge is right here on this door you don't
see the hinge. The hinge is in the pantry, it's not in
this room, right? Yeah for this would be-
that door is set up, the way that door is set up
the main- the outside is beyond.
Right. So that's what- that's exactly what it's saying. It's not whether
the hinge is on the left or the right. It's whether the
hinge is which side of the door. Because the hinge is on
the other side of the door, then the basic way of assumed
travel is from this side to that side, from where you don't
see the hinge to where you do see the hinge. That's the-
where we are the outside we don't see the hinge and the
assumed way of travel is from the side of the door where
we don't see the hinge to the side of the door where
we do see the hinge.
So you- you made this correct distinction before that exterior door you
care about that with interior
door you don't really care about that, right? Because exterior door you
don't want your right- what good is a lock if your hinges
are exposed to the outside of an exterior door? Right. So anyway-
anyway so that is what the גמרא Gemara is saying that the
side that the hinge is on is considered to be the inside.
Did we assume that door was hinges in the setup that we
have now? Because usually when we're talking about like
the- when the גמרא Gemara talks about the doors and doorways and
stuff he thinks it like inserts and they come off. Right.
So yeah I mean they wasn't exactly the same like metal hinges
but there still was some you know mechanism of a peg in
a hole to allow for the thing to move around. Okay so
now the גמרא Gemara says and now the גמרא Gemara spells out
that we are specifically talking about a door between rooms because if
the door is to literally the street or the house you know
which is the basic way you move, you move from the street
into the house. So we're talking specifically about a door between rooms.
So let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara says היכי דמי, Heichi
Dami, what is the case in which this is relevant? So it
says כגון פתחא דבין תרי בתי, Ke-goan pitcha de-vein t'rei vatei,
like a- a door between two houses out of the houses or
rooms, בין בי גברי לבין בי נשי. Bein bei gavrei le-vein bei
nashei.
So you see the men and women were kept separate so here
you have you have the men's part of the house and the
women's part and you have a little room a door that opens
between so which way is considered to be the flow of traffic?
From the men's to the women's or the women's side to the
men's side? So it goes from based on where the hinge is
that determines what the conceptually the flow of traffic from the side
of the door that there isn't a hinge to the side of
the door where there is a hinge. Now again what I said
about this question about assuming interior rooms you know when the גמרא
Gemara here refers to a men's half and a women's half בי
נשי בי גברי Bei nashei bei gavrei it sounds like you know
conceptually it's closer to the idea of two houses you know or
really two fundamentally different living spaces as opposed to just you know
what we would say a living room a dining room interior rooms.
But again you know while there is some question I really raised
this as an academic point not that for everybody to make it
or anything no but you know because it's always we universally assume
that we do require מזוזות Mezuzot on interior rooms but it's not
as clear as we might expect that in the גמרא Gemara when
you realize that גמרא Gemara was dealing more with each separate room
was often a separate domicile. Okay so let's continue. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
ריש גלותא בנא ביתא, Resh Galuta bana beita, so the ריש גלותא
Resh Galuta which was the secular head Jewish head of the Jews
in גלות- Galut in you know Babylonia built his house. אמר ליה
לרב נחמן, Amar lei le-Rav Nachman, he says to רב נחמן, Rav
Nachman, רב נחמן Rav Nachman was like what for this guy was
exactly was a relative and was the halakhic authority they always went
to. So they went to רב נחמן Rav Nachman and they said
קבע לי מזוזתא, Kava li mezuzeta, okay I just built a house
go put up the מזוזות. Mezuzot. So אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav
Nachman, so רב נחמן Rav Nachman said תלי דשי ברישא, Tali dashei
be-reisha, first put up the doors then put up the מזוזות. Mezuzot.
Why? So רש"י Rashi says he wanted there to be a doorframe
because you have to put a מזוזה Mezuzah in a doorframe and
you can't first put the מזוזה Mezuzah in the sort of space
carved out and then put the doorframe. That's an interesting question of
the need for a physical doorframe. One minute. תוספות Tosafot says no
no no this is exactly what the discussion we just had. He
wanted to know which way was the flow of traffic between the
rooms. So he says I can't tell until you put up the
doors and you put in the hinges then I'll be able to
determine which way is the flow of traffic and I'll be able
to put the מזוזה Mezuzah on the right side of the archways
the doorways.
But mostly the מזוזות Mezuzot were by like stone in a certain
spot so in other words it is a different type of מזוזה
Mezuzah they talking about the ideal מזוזה Mezuzah but I thought
they'd carve it in the- no well I mean in Israel definitely
I mean if you had stone doorways you put- you carved a
hole in the stone. If you had wood frames you would put
it in the wood. But it is true Michael just pointed out
that the גמרא Gemara here I mean sometimes it speaks about קבע
מזוזה Kava mezuzah fixing a מזוזה Mezuzah which might sound like nailing
it on and so on but it's not clear how much the
גמרא's Gemara referring to having it on the- on the outside you
know if you nailed on as opposed to actually insert it. into
the frame it says itself itself. So I don't, that's not fully
clear from these descriptions. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says,
now we get to a very famous גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Let's take
a look. אמר רב Rav יהודה אמר רב Rav, *Amar Rav Yehuda
Amar Rav*. So רב Rav, יהודה *Rav Yehuda* said in the name
of רב Rav, *Rav*, he comes up here a lot in these
מזוזה Mezuzah? *Mezuzah* discussions. עשאה כמין נגר פסולה psulah, *Asa'ah kemin nagar
pesulah*. If you make it like a נגר *nagar*, it's invalid. So
if you look at רש"י Rashi *Rashi*’s picture here, it basically means
you stuck it in horizontal into the door frame, not vertical, but
you basically banged it in horizontal like a נגר *nagar*, it's invalid.
איני Aini, *Eeini* says the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*, is this true? והא
כי אתא רב יצחק בר יוסף אמר *Veha ki ata Rav Yitzchak
bar Yosef amar* when רב יצחק בר יוסף *Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef*
came, he said: כולם מזוזות mezuzot דבי רבי Rebbi, *Kulam mezuzot devei
Rebbe*, all of the מזוזות mezuzot *mezuzot* in רבי Rebbi. *Rebbe*’s house,
כמין נגר הוו עבידן *kemine nagar havei avidun*, they were like this
נגר *nagar*, like this sort of nail post, or let's say a
nail. So you see it's כשר *kosher*. וההוא פתחא *Vehahu pitcha* and
now parenthetically, a point we'll get back to in a minute, וההוא
פתחא דעייל ביה רבי Rebbi לבי מדרשא *vehahu pitcha de'ayeil beih Rebbe
levei midrasha*, that door that רבי *Rebbe* would use to exit his
house, apparently he had a בית מדרש Beis Medrash. *Beit Midrash* attached
as a side room to his house, and he had a little
room, a little, in one room he had a little private door
he would use to sneak into his בית מדרש Beis Medrash *Beit
Midrash*. Okay, all the students would go in through the main exit,
but he would have this little interior door. So that little door
that he used to go into his בית מדרש Beis Medrash *Beit
Midrash*, לא הוה ליה מזוזה Mezuzah, *lo hava lei Mezuzah*, did not
have a מזוזה Mezuzah *Mezuzah*. So we'll talk about his בית מדרש
Beis Medrash, *Beit Midrash* door in a minute, but now let's focus
on how his מזוזה Mezuzah *Mezuzah* was fixed. So it says he
did it like a נגר *nagar*, like this nail, so you see
it's okay. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, what's the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*’s answer? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: לא קשיא *lo kashya*,
it's not difficult. הא דעבידא כסיכתא *ha de'avidah kesichta*, in one case
it's made like a סיכתא *sichta*, which is again like this peg,
which is horizontal, which is no good. הא דעבידא כאיסתבירא *ha de'avidah
ke'istavira*. And the other's that it's made like an איסתבירא *istavira*. What
is an איסתבירא *istavira*? So an איסתבירא *istavira* is the joint that
connects from the side to the, from the hip to the thigh.
So what does that mean? So רש"י *Rashi* says, has two explanations,
one or actually two, and תוספות Tosafot's *Tosafot* has a third. What
does it mean? That the same way, you know, if your hip
and your thigh here, it's vertical if you're standing up. So again,
when we say like a nail it's invalid, we mean a horizontal
nail it's invalid. But if it's like a vertical nail, then it
is valid. Okay, pretty funny way to just say we mean vertical.
The other explanation רש"י *Rashi* has is that if you're sitting, the
way your joint works is it creates a right angle, right? So
if you look at this little second picture of רש"י *Rashi*, you
see the מזוזה Mezuzah *Mezuzah* that's bent underneath the horizontal one? Right,
you see the white space in the second picture of רש"י *Rashi*?
So horizontal is no good, but if you have it like horizontal
and vertical bent, then it is good. Who is bothering to carve
a bent hole into their thing to make it very strange? But
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says what?
It's a tombstone, maybe? Oh,
that could be, that would
be, you would bend the קלף *klaf*.
Then you, yeah, you would bend the קלף *klaf*. You'll break it,
you'll bend it, it's קלף *klaf*. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says that no,
איסתבירא *istavira* means at a diagonal. Okay, which makes a certain degree
of sense, it's not horizontal, it's not vertical, it's diagonal, you could
imagine also that type of a cut. Now more significantly, תוספות Tosafot,
*Tosafot* says, argues on what the לכתחילה l'chatchila *lechatchila* is, because we
said that רבי *Rebbe* did it at this funny angle, whatever that
is. But the לכתחילה *lechatchila* is, or you're not allowed to do
it like a peg. So what should you do it at? רש"י
*Rashi* says you should do it vertical, which is the way we
have it. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* reads the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* the exact
opposite. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says a peg means a vertical peg, that's
not allowed. So what are you supposed to do? You're supposed to
do horizontal. Okay, and תוספות Tosafot, *Tosafot* says you know why? Because
actually this is different, you know, we are very used to the
idea that our ספרי תורה Sifrei Torah *Sifrei Torah* are kept in
the ארון Aron *Aron*, right, vertical, that that's a respectful. But I
think in some Sephardic communities, and the way they actually keep the
ספרי תורה Torah *Sifrei Torah* are lying flat. Is that correct? I
actually think, no, maybe I'm wrong because the Sephardi have them in
their whole case. But there definitely are places where ספרי תורה Torah
*Sifrei Torah* were kept actually lying flat. And that actually was considered
more respectful, you know, it's not in this awkward situation, you know,
you're setting it down. So store, I mean if
you're...
Right,
there's a difference between storage and, correct. So but תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*
assumes that the peg that's invalid is vertical and what's actually acceptable
is horizontal. He actually says the same issues about how you put
the קלף *klaf* in the תפילין tefillin *Tefillin*. Do you put the
קלף *klaf* in the תפילין tefillin *Tefillin* standing up or lying flat?
So, so then you get this major debate. So according to רש"י
*Rashi*, I'm supposed to put it vertical. According to תוספות Tosafot, *Tosafot*,
I'm supposed to put it horizontal. What do I do? So you
could just פסקן pasken, *pasken*.
But תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* himself suggests that maybe if we interpret that
what רבי *Rebbe*’s house was, was the angle, the diagonal, right, that's
תוספות *Tosafot*’s reader what רבי *Rebbe*’s house was. So now everybody will
be happy, because even if רש"י *Rashi* would say לכתחילה *lechatchila* vertical,
and רבנו תם *Rabbeinu Tam* would say לכתחילה *lechatchila* horizontal, maybe they
could all agree that at a diagonal, that's a true קיום kiyum
*kiyum* of a פשרה *peshara*, of a compromise, 45,
each one has to move 45 degrees, and if you do it
at the diagonal, then
it... Nevertheless,
nevertheless, there definitely were those that just ruled straight like רש"י *Rashi*,
the Vilna Gaon I don't know of anybody who ruled straight like
רבנו תם *Rabbeinu Tam*. The Vilna Gaon ruled straight like רש"י *Rashi*,
and in ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim* I think it's very common that you'll
see מזוזות *mezuzot* which follows מנהגי הגר"א *minhagei haGra*, you will see
the מזוזות *mezuzot* that are completely straight vertical. Even when we do
it at an angle, we do not do a 45-degree angle. We
do like what, like a 20 or 30-degree angle, we primarily do
it vertically. So that's in terms of the debate of רש"י *Rashi*
and רבנו תם *Rabbeinu Tam*. I didn't go put up on the
website, but I made for you today the pictures from the first
volume of Daniel Sperber's מנהגי ישראל *Minhagei Yisrael*. I have many more
people today at the שיעור shiur, *shiur* than I expected, everybody heard
we're doing מזוזה Mezuzah, *mezuzah*, so share some from Daniel Sperber's מנהגי
ישראל *Minhagei Yisrael*. Before Daniel Sperber got into the whole מנהגים minhagim.
*minhagim* business, he was a, he was a, what do you call
it? His real field of focus was much more about the realia
at the time of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, you know, sort of
using archaeology and whatever to understand the realia. And he shows that
the houses that were in ישראל *Israel* at the time, why are
we talking about a נגר *nagar*, a peg? And he basically says
the peg is the doorbolt. When the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* refers to
the נגר *nagar* as פסול *pasul*, it means the doorbolt. And he
says if you look at the homes in ישראל *Israel* in, you
know, from the ancient archaeological digs, you will find, now he has
actually real pictures, you know, diagrams, but the pictures are very hard
even in the original to see what he's talking about. These are
what the pictures look like, doors
and a נגר *nagar*,
they're not so comprehensible, you could try to look at that, the
resolution is, but if you look here at תמונה ד' *temuna daled*,
he says this is a classic door frame, that one side which
was straight column of stone, one piece of stone, and the other
side which was a broken stone. You know why they, two stones.
You know why they had specifically made this, sort of like what
you were saying, they specifically made two stones so there would be
a hole in the middle so you could use it for your
doorbolt on the inside. And that was the נגר *nagar*, and he
actually says that a number of them, as we're about to see
in a minute, we know we put the מזוזה Mezuzah? *mezuzah* at
about a third from the top of the frame, and he says
although here it shows in the middle, he says a lot of
them actually the doorbolt was about a third from the top from
the frame, so that this is exactly the נגר *nagar*, and he
says which supports רש"י'ס *Rashi's* read that this is what's invalid. Don't
use your מזוזה Mezuzah. *mezuzah*, you know, don't squeeze it into the
hole that you made basically for your doorbolt. And he says I,
we have also found sort of bolt holes that were on an
angle like the way תוספות *Tosafot* explains the house of רבי *Rebbe*,
that they were at an angle. We have never found anything that
was basically fundamentally
horizontal. Vertical, what you do have here is of course here's something
which is like you would, I don't exactly understand the mechanism, but
like it would sort of, I well actually I do, it would
sort of hold it down at the bottom there, right, and as
well as bolted at the top. But anyway, he makes the excellent
point that, you know, we did have angled ones and we did
have horizontal ones and the idea of נגר *nagar* is exactly like
the type of a bolt. Don't make it like this doorbolt. So
anyway, so that is the general ruling is like רש"י *Rashi*, although
we try to do תוספות'ס *Tosafot's* compromise of doing it at an
angle. If you have a very narrow door and you really can't
do much of an angle, so you just do it straight, you
know, vertical.
The other thing I was going to say which he does not
discuss, but I have heard and I don't know if there's any
evidence for, is that specifically in אשכנז *Ashkenaz*, because this idea of
angle was a specifically in אשכנז *Ashkenaz*. I think in ספרד *Sefard*
they had no problem to do it straight vertical. But specifically in
אשכנז *Ashkenaz* the מנהג minhag *minhag* was to do it at an
angle and I've heard people surmise, I don't know if there's any
evidence to this, that it had to do with the time of
the Crusades because if the מזוזה Mezuzah? *mezuzah* was as straight vertical,
that apparently that the Crusaders would come when they went into a
Jewish place, I guess when they weren't killing and raping them, and
they would just take a piece of wood and they would put,
they would smack it horizontal on the מזוזה Mezuzah *mezuzah* and turn
it into a cross, and so that what they did was they
made them an angle so you couldn't do that. Again, that might
be legend, I don't know, I have to see if there's any
evidence for that. Okay, so that's how the תוספות *Tosafot* explains this,
that the whole thing is talking about horizontal, that he says is
more respectful based on how they were stored. Just let's just see
the last line of that תוספות *Tosafot* so you see it inside.
It's the, it's the תוספות *Tosafot* הדעבידא *had'avida* not והא *veha*. It's
about, but it's the line right above the word והא *veha*, the
big new תוספות *Tosafot* והא *veha*. He says ואומר רבנו תם *u'omer
Rabbeinu Tam*, צא ולמד *tzei u'lemad*, see we're in the פסח *Pesach*
mode, צא ולמד *tzei u'lemad* דהוה מעשה בכל יום *d'hava maiseh bechol
yom*, every day, כשספר תורה עומד על הבימה *k'she'sefer Torah omeid al
ha'bima*,
when they put it standard on the בימה *bima*, הכל עומדים *hakol
omdim*, everybody stands, וכששליח ציבור מושיבו *uk'she'shaliach tzibbur moshivo*, when
he lies it down, הכל יושבים *hakol yoshvim*, everybody sits. Now what
is that supposed to prove? Presumably it proves that standing is an
unnatural state of it and lying down is the natural state, and
therefore he understands that the proper way to put קלפים *klafim* and
מזוזות *mezuzot* and even in the תפילין tefillin *t'fillin* is horizontal, not
vertical. vertical. Okay, but we do not rule that way. We primarily
rule רש״י, Rashi although the מנהג minhag is to do it at
an angle, like the תוספות read of the איצטווירא. istavira.
What? אשכנז ספרד Ashkenaz Sfarad read it standing up. Right.
Lying down.
For ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. Right. So our ספרי תורה we do
standing up, but it also is a little awkward, you need the
chains and you need whatever.
No, no, no, we read it lying down.
Oh, read it lying down. Oh, that's interesting.
Right, that's interesting, that's interesting. תוספות says that it's kept in the
ארון lying down. That was his practice.
That reading standing up or lying down, yeah, I mean I think
that's not in the גמרא, Gemara. how it was done. That's a
difference of מנהגים. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara goes on,
where are we?
איני, Aini, the גמרא. Gemara Now we're back to this little door
that רב used to access his בית מדרש. Beis Medrash. Why did
that not need a מזוזה? Mezuzah So this, the way רש״י Rashi,
explains this, it has to do with the fact that it's like,
you know, a tiny little private door, that the real way you
get into the בית מדרש Beis Medrash, is a main entrance, but
רב, not רב, רבי, you know, he had his main room and
when he had to sneak into this other room to give his
שיעור, shiur he had the little private doorway to get into the
other room. So therefore it didn't need a מזוזה, Mezuzah, it was
just his private doorway. So the גמרא Gemara says איני, Aini, so
apparently there's an assumption that it has to be a, you know,
a significant doorway. But you're right, we're not learning it from פסוקים,
pesukim, a lot of this is just assumed. So the גמרא Gemara,
says איני, is this true? בההוא פיתחא דהוה עייל ביה רב הונא
לבי מדרשא, Bahahu pitcha de'hava ayei ba Rav Huna l'bei midrasha, there
was a little door that רב הונא Rav Huna used to get
into the בית מדרש Beis Medrash דהוה ליה מזוזה, de'hava lei Mezuzah,
and there was a מזוזה Mezuzah. there. So the גמרא Gemara says
ההוא רגיל הוה, hahu ragil hava,
that was a door that he was either he used very commonly
or it was common for other people to use the door, so
it was a real door as opposed to a, you know, a
real passageway as opposed to רבי. Again the parameters here are not
that clear.
רבי didn't give a שיעור shiur. that often? What? Meaning like if
they're both using this door to go into the שיעור.
I know, so I'm saying we don't have a good quantitative definition.
תוספות by the way about it being a בית מדרש, Beis Medrash
if you look at the first line of the next תוספות, לההוא
פיתחא דהוה בי רב הונא והוה ליה מזוזה, Le'hahu pitcha de'hava bei
Rav Huna ve'hava lei Mezuzah, so תוספות says מתוך הלשון משמע דוקא
פתח הבית שהיו יוצאים ממנו לבית מדרש. mitoch ha'lashon mashma davka petach
habayit she'hayu yotzim mimenu l'Beis Medrash.
The reason it required a מזוזה Mezuzah was not because it was
a door to the בית מדרש. It was a door leaving your
house. It was a house door, it was just going to the
בית מדרש, but the need for the מזוזה Mezuzah was because it
was a house door. He says אבל פתח בית המדרש עצמו, aval
petach Beis ha'Medrash atzmo, if you just had a door to the
בית מדרש עצמו, atzmo, that לא בעי מזוזה lo ba'ei Mezuzah would
not need a מזוזה, Mezuzah and then he goes to discuss that
whole case. It's sort of like קרח'ס Korach's question to משה, Moshe,
בית מלא ספרים, bayis malei sefarim, you know, does it need a
מזוזה? Mezuzah And the actual answer is no! Because it's not a
place where you live. So actually, you know, בית כנסת Beis Knesset
and בית מדרש and so on, if you don't have anybody actually
sleeping there and living there, does not על פי דין al pi
din really require a מזוזה.
Mezuzah But the מנהג we put one anyway.
Yeah, we do it on בסיס המנהג. basis haminhag. So now back
to the גמרא. Gemara So the גמרא Gemara says like this: Okay,
I'm sorry, I didn't finish the line in the גמרא. Gemara ההוא
רגיל הוה דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב ומזוזה הלך אחר הרגיל. hahu
ragil hava d'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav u'mezuzah halach achar haragil.
Go by what is common. So now what does that mean? Does
that mean if you have a door that's only rarely used it's
not required a מזוזה? mezuza Look at רש״י, Rashi הלך אחר הרגיל.
halach achar haragil. רש״י Rashi is about ten lines from the bottom.
אם יש שני פתחים לחדר אחד באותו פתח שרגיל לצאת ולבא יותר
יניח המזוזה. im yesh shenei petachim l'cheder echad be'oto petach sheragil latzeis
velavo yoser yaniach hamezuzah.
Very much unlike we assume. רש״י says, you know, you only have
to identify one real door for a room. Now as it goes
to different places, like that door goes to the pantry and that
door goes to the hallway, but if you have two doors that
both go into a similar space and one is your main door
and the other is a secondary, your side door, you don't need
a מזוזה mezuza. to the secondary door, because presumably the logic is
you already have a מזוזה mezuza. in the passageway from room A
to room B, the primary passageway, so it's not just that the
door frame requires a מזוזה, mezuza, if it doesn't represent a, you
know, a different way, a different passage of A to B, you
do not require מזוזה. mezuza So again the parameters here are not
exactly clear, exactly how to quantify this, but this is what we
are now saying that the reason the door did not require מזוזה
mezuzah was it was not the main door to get out. Okay.
אמר רב זירא אמר רב, Amar Rav Zeira Amar Rav, back to
the גמרא. Gemara זירא Zeira said in the name of רב, אמר
רב מתנא אמר שמואל, amar Rav Matna Amar Shmuel, מצוה להניח בתחילת
שליש העליון, mitzvah lehaniach bit'chilat shelish ha'elyon, this is what we do.
It is a מצוה mitzvah to put the מזוזה mezuzah. in the
top third of the door.
Meaning the bottom part of it should be
in the top, the מזוזה mezuzah right, the מזוזה mezuzah. ends at
the bottom of the top third. Okay, so you go two thirds
from the ground and that the bottom point where the מזוזה mezuzah.
should end, okay, it was in the top third of the door.
רב הונא אמר, Rav Huna amar, רב הונא Rav Huna says מגביה
מן הקרקע טפח ומרחיק מן הקורה טפח, magbia min hakarka tefach u'marchyik
min hakora tefach, no, you have a much broader place you can
put it.
It should be above the bottom טפח tefach from the ground, below
the bottom טפח tefach from the ceiling, וכל הפתח כולו כשר למזוזה,
ve'chol hapetach kulo kasher limzuzah, and you can really put it anywhere
in the frame. Now they don't necessarily argue, the other phrase was
מצוה להניח, mitzvah lehaniach, so it might be ideally it should be
there but בדיעבד bedieved it could be anywhere in it. And that's
possible. Now why should it be in that top third? It could
very well be because so we should see it when we pass
it. It's supposed to be a זכרון zikaron
but that's not the case if it's like the gate of a
city, a שער. sha'ar. Then it's presumably it's much higher and then
you wouldn't...
Right, if it's beyond where you can reach, the top third isn't
going to help you. We'll talk about that in a minute. תוספות
quotes ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. Okay,
so let's take a look.
Usually like children's room, with little kids maybe you could put the
מזוזה mezuzah lower.
Ah, so for better קיום of the מצוה, mitzvah, that's a good
point too. Yep, but then they grow up though. All right, anyway,
okay, so let's take a look. דברי רבי יהודה, Divrei Rabbi Yehuda,
that's what Rabbi Yehuda said. I'm sorry, did I skip a line?
No.
מיתיבי, Meiseiv, they asked on this. Here's a ברייתא: baraita: מגביה מן
הקרקע טפח ומרחיק מן הקורה טפח וכל הפתח כולו כשר למזוזה, magbiha
min hakarka tefach u'marchik min hakora tefach v'chol hapetach kulo kasher l'mezuza,
דברי רבי יהודה. divrei Rabbi Yehuda. So Rabbi Yehuda says anywhere that's
not the bottom or the top טפח. tefach. רבי יוסי אומר
וקשרתם וכתבתם, Rabbi Yose omer u'kshartem u'chtavtem, he makes the comparing the
two verbs, bind the תפילין and write the מזוזה. mezuzah מה קשירה
בגובה, ma kshira begova, the same way you bind the תפילין it's
on the top part of your body, either on your head or
on the upper part of your arm, so therefore אף כתיבה בגובה,
af ktiva begova, so
the writing has to be on the top. So we understand the
top here means he's talking about actually the... over
the שערות se'arot although the גובה gova וקשרתם וקשרתם אותם על ידכם
והיו לטטפת, u'kshartem u'kshartem osam al yedchem vehayu l'totafot, it's really on
the שערות... se'arot... anyway, it has to be on the very top.
So he's not just saying the top third, he would be saying
really at the top. Within the closest of the טפח tefach even?
Well, not close ever, but certainly not just within the top third,
as close as possible to the top. Okay, maybe not in the
top טפח. tefach. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara, says: בשלמא
לרב הונא, bishlama le'Rav Huna,
according to Rav Huna that says you have the entire doorframe except
for the top and bottom טפח, tefach, הוא דאמר כרבי יהודה, hu
de'amar k'Rabbi Yehuda, he says like Rabbi Yehuda that says exactly that.
אלא שמואל דאמר כמאן? ella Shmuel de'amar keman? Shmuel who says the
top third, who's he going like? לא כרבי יהודה, lo k'Rabbi Yehuda,
not Rabbi Yehuda that says you have the entire doorframe, ולא כרבי
יוסי, v'lo k'Rabbi Yose, and not like Rabbi Yose who says it's
to be at the presumably at the very top. So אמר רב
הונא בריה דרב נתן, amar Rav Huna brei de'Rav Natan, לעולם כרבי
יוסי, l'olam k'Rabbi Yose, he's going like Rabbi Yose, ומאי תילתא עילייתא,
u'mai tilta elayeta, what does Shmuel mean when he says the top
third? דקאמר להרחיקה, de'ka amar l'harchika, he means that don't go any
lower than the top third, שלא להרחיקה מן הקורה שלמעלה יותר משליש,
she'lo l'harchika min hakora she'mala yoter mishlish, don't go any lower than
the top third, but maybe לכתחילה he would agree it should be
the higher the better. Now according to this, we don't have the
way we פסקן, pasken right? Because the one that says the top
third is actually saying as low as you can get is the
top third but ideally it's the very top. We
actually פסקן pasken exactly at that top third level. So if you
take a look at תוספות, תוספות says ומאי תילתא עילייתא דקאמר להרחיקה
שיותר לא ירחיקנה. u'mai tilta elayeta de'ka amar l'harchika she'yoter lo yarchikenu.
ובירושלמי משמע דכי הוי פתח גבוה הרבה, u'veYerushalmi mashma d'chesha petach gavo'ah
harbei, here you go, when you have a very high one,
מניחה כנגד כתפיו, menicho k'neged ktefav, you put it up basically where
your shoulders would be, it should be at shoulder height. וחולק על
הש"ס שלנו. ve'cholik al hashas shelanu. So we actually, I have to
check the הלכה halakha about what happens when you do have very
high one, presumably it is like תוספות, I think what I remember
in ירושלים Yerushalayim when you had those big arches they put it
more or less at shoulder height.
Well those ירושלים Yerushalayim. ones were like ירושלמי Yerushalmi presumably.
ירושלמי Yerushalmi was not written in ירושלים. Yerushalayim, There was no גמרא
Gemara written in ירושלים, it's quite interesting. תלמוד ירושלמי Talmud Yerushalmi is
called תלמודא דארץ ישראל, Talmuda d'Eretz Yisrael, it was in Caesarea, anyway,
whatever.
But okay, but we פסקן pasken actually we know the top third
but not the lower part of the top third, not to say
it's better to do it higher, which is not like the פשט
pshat of the way our גמרא Gemara concludes. Okay, so now we
go on. אמר רבא, amar Rava, so Rava says,
מצוה להניחה, mitzvah l'hani-cha, this is the Rava we quoted before, that
was now so now know the vertical. The vertical is either anywhere
or as high as possible or what we פסקן which is not
clear in the גמרא, Gemara the top third. Now we're going to
talk about the horizontal, the thickness, where within the thickness of the
doorframe. So we quoted this before, אמר רבא מצוה להניחה בטפח הסמוך
לרשות הרבים, amar Rava mitzvah l'hani-cha b'tefach hasamuch l'reshut harabim, it should
be in the טפח tefach closest to the outside of the door
in terms of the thickness. Like חנוכה Chanukah like? Right, well, same
idea. מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the reason? רבנן אמרי כדי שיפגע
במזוזה מיד, Rabbanan amri kedei she'yifga b'mezuza miyad, that as soon as
you walk in the house, the first thing you bump into is
the מזוזה. mezuzah So again, this is talking very much about the
personal psychological religious experience. You would encounter the מזוזה, mezuzah, okay. Now
מיד, miyad, רב חנינא מסורא אמר, Rav Chanina mi-Sura amar, now here
we get this other aspect, כי היכי דתינטריה, ki heichi d'tinaterei, in
order that the מזוזה mezuzah? should protect you. So if you want
it to protect the whole house, you want it the protection to
start at the very
outer limits, at the very beginning of the house. You don't want
to go even a טפח tefach into the house unprotected. You should
put it on your exterior wall then. Okay, but here again you
see this idea that it's not this idea of like because you're
doing a מצוה mitzvah God is protecting you, there's almost a charm
aspect of it. So exactly where it's situated is going to determine
the parameters of which part of the house is protected. Which is
also a strange thing, it
protects the whole door, why
is it conflating these two? That's a good point. רמב״ם Rambam who
does not buy into any of this charm and superstition, whatever, he
basically says by your religious, psychological awareness of what the מזוזה mezuzah,
is, that is what affords you protection. Right. That's very nicely said.
But in the גמרא Gemara they're presented as different positions.
Okay, so why isn't it just a practical matter?
Why isn't it simply practical? If you're going to put it sometimes
on the side that has the hinge, ah,
because the door is
going to open and the door is going to open from the
inside.
So why not to put it behind the door altogether? But if
you have a very thick doorframe and the door starts three טפחים
tefachim in, you could put it in front of the door but
still more than a טפח, tefach, you know, into the thickness. So
you're right. If it's behind the door we don't even have to
explain why you don't want it behind the door because then it
gets hidden. But the question is even in front of the door
we want it as outer as possible.
All right, why it's on the inside not on the outside of
the doorframe?
Well that's because the גמרא Gemara said בשעריך, bisharecha, which is in
in your gates, inside, not on the outside. That's just how they
understand the פסוק. pasuk. Okay. So in order that it should protect
you. אמר רבי חנינא Amar Rabbi Hanina and now we actually talk
about what I like now is the shift though. Notice the גמרא
Gemara does not say קנטרי מינה מזיקין kintarei mina mazikin or whatever,
you know, although קנטרי kintarei the the subject of the verb is
the מזוזה. mezuzah It seems to be. But the מזוזה mezuzah should
protect you, but now the גמרא Gemara. does an immediate shift to
talk about God. So let's take a look. Okay. אמר רבי חנינא
Amar Rabbi Hanina בוא וראה שלא כמדת הקדוש ברוך הוא מדת בשר
ודם. Bo u're'e shelo kemidat Hakadosh Baruch Hu midat basar vadam. The
way God acts is not the way people act. מדת בשר ודם,
midat basar vadam, the way a human being acts, flesh and blood,
מלך יושב מבפנים ועם משמרים אותו מבחוץ. melech yoshev mibifnim ve'am m'shamrim
oto mibachutz.
The king sits in his inner chamber and he has all the
guards and people protecting him on all in all of the outside
of the chamber. מדת
הקדוש ברוך הוא אינו כן. midat Hakadosh Baruch Hu eino ken. This
is not how God works. עבדיו יושבים מבפנים והוא משמר מבחוץ. avadav
yoshvim mibifnim vehu m'shamer mibachutz.
God protects them from outside the house. שנאמר shene'emar as the פסוק
pasuk says ה׳ שמרך ה׳ צלך על יד ימינך. Hashem shomrecha Hashem
tzilcha al yad yeminecha. God will protect you,
God will be on the right hand. So what I think the
גמרא Gemara? is doing and you find this other places as well
and we actually yeah exactly the גמרא, Gemara. you know,
we often read the גמרא Gemara as if the גמרא Gemara is
dictating what the religion should be or what the הלכה halakha should
be certainly. But we sometimes lose sight of the fact that, you
know, people were practicing whatever they were practicing and I don't just
mean הלכתית halakhically but sort of the religious significance they assign to
it and so on. And sometimes the גמרא Gemara does a beautiful
job of like sort of almost downplaying those more superstitious approaches by
not even acknowledging them. By just talking about things in their הלכה
halakha categories. So what you have here, I mean I think that
happens a lot by נדה niddah by example which we'll get to
not too far from now where there was clearly a lot of
taboos that were associated with נדה niddah and the גמרא Gemara refuses
to attend to those. The גמרא Gemara just looks at it through
a הלכה halakha lens, which in a way discounts that other approach.
So here I think you could say the same thing is happening
by מזוזה. mezuzah Clearly, I mean if we have any good archaeological
evidence of anything, it was the use of קמיעות kameot and charms
and magical amulets going way back into the, you know, clearly even
in the בית שני bayis sheni period. This is not a new
thing. So clearly people were associating magical powers with the מזוזה. mezuzah
But what the גמרא Gemara does is it downplays it, right? The
first explanation is psychological, your פוגע. pogeah. The second it will protect
you, but it doesn't elaborate on that and then it immediately shifts
into God protects you ה׳ שמרך, Hashem shomrecha, ה׳ צלך Hashem tzilcha
so almost like Mordechai said the conflating of the religious experience with
God protecting you and bracketing the, you know, the charm aspect here,
the magical aspect seems to be part of the agenda of the
גמרא. Gemara, Yes.
Even want people to be superstitious that you wouldn't
have
the word קנטרי kintarei at all in the גמרא? Gemara Yeah. Most
people's experience was not based on reading the גמרא. Gemara Their religious
experience being where you're supposed to... oh you wouldn't have what?
נן דה וובקא? nun de vuvka? Really? Yeah. Because it invites it.
And you go out of your way to not think that it's
there to somehow protect you or the house or that there isn't
some sort of a power. For me even people say when there's
bad luck check
מזוזות right.
Yeah then more of like a folk tale than really a you
know a awareness
what? You mentioned wearing the מזוזה mezuzah.
around as a necklace or having like the מזוזה mezuzah? but actually
I see them more as like the king with the ספר תורה.
Sefer Torah. Right as a זכר. zecher.
Started to wear it around. And well
it depends what the people are thinking. Right, that it's a protection.
Right, that's not about protection, that's about your...
you're not... that's a constraint of power.
So here's an interesting question I would ask: would it be the
same if it were not in a case? If you actually had
the מזוזה mezuzah? flat and readable on the doorpost, right, I think
somehow it's being in a case that gives it that power like
an amuletic power to it.
I think that'd also be like
a very...
but it also could be true about the תפילין as well. You
know, but I think when they're in case and we haven't yet
really seen that but we're going to... in a minute the idea
about putting it in a tube, what's the
אידיאלע שמאַנטי ideale shmanti case business now?
But still no,
I'm just saying the fact, the fact that something is encased makes
it almost created as an amulet. I'm wondering if you just had
וכתבתם על מזוזות ביתך, Ukhtavtam al mezuzot beitekha, you just had the
parchment, you know, right there flat down and you could read it,
whether you would feel that this is an amulet even if no
magical or not. But I understand that, I don't know what to
say.
I mean, it still is the thing in the מזוזה, mezuzah? right?
Right. What's the idea of ומשמרך u-mishmarkha especially when you identify yourself
as part of it, right? Right, okay.
But the question also is and then but but the blood and
the power of blood and whatever, I mean, you easily translate that
as something more magical and less less religious and פסוקים pesukim that
that
I don't know if anything דווקא davka by מצרים Mitzrayim it sounds
like there is some power, ולא יתן המשחית לבוא אל בתיכם לנגוף.
v'lo yiten hamashchit lavo el bateikhem lingof. I mean, I don't know.
Anyway, all right. So yeah, but you know, I
think part of the reason the גמרא also is here is because
we just talked about that you should put it in as far
out as possible, so this you know.
Right, so that was the context, as far out, right.
It's also God protects from out, so put it as far out
as possible, show to God.
But is it God or is it the מזוזה? mezuzah Right, okay,
so now it
goes back again three days in a row, so the question of
what is this thing. If you're right, does it have a magical
force?
Well, that is the issue by the מזוזה, mezuzah. clearly people did
think that. I really think the גמרא is
subtly trying to either ignore that or rework that. That's my sense.
Okay, so let's keep on reading. דרש רב יוסף Darash Rav Yosef
בריה דרבא משמיה דרבא. brei de-Rava mishmei de-Rava. So Rav Yosef son
of Rava explained in the name of Rava, העמיקה טפח פסולה. he-emikah
tefakh pesulah.
If you dig the מזוזה mezuzah in deeper than a טפח tefakh
into the doorframe, it's invalid. Okay.
You must have a thick doorframe.
Yeah, yeah, thick doorframe.
What? Cases of the wall. That's right, the wall, not the doorframe,
or too far in, correct. So the גמרא says, לימא מסייע ליה,
leima mesaye'a lei, let's try to bring a proof to this. We
have the following ברייתא. braita. הניחה בפצין, hinikhah b-fatzin, so פצין fatzin
presumably are also like the doorframe, the the או שתלה עליה מלבן,
o she-talah aleha malben,
or you attached a a stone to the doorframe after having placed
the מזוזה mezuzah there.
Wait, what was the פצין fatzin again?
It's the doorframe. אם יש שם טפח תחת מזוזה אחרת אם לאו
אין תחת מזוזה אחרת. im yesh sham tefakh takhat mezuzah akheret im
lav ein takhat mezuzah akheret.
So if it is now that the מזוזה mezuzah is so buried
deep into the doorframe that it's more than a טפח tefakh into
the doorframe itself, right? Until now we've been talking about the vertical
and the width, I assume now we're talking about the depth. Right?
So like, you understand? So now into the wall essentially, then it's
like the מזוזה mezuzah isn't part of the doorframe and then you
need another מזוזה. mezuzah. So this seems to be an exact support
of what we just said.
או שתלה עליה מלבן. o she-talah aleha malben.
Yeah, you stuck a stone over, like, yeah, you sort of stoned
up your doorframe and now what used to be your doorframe is
now deeper in and now your doorframe is made by these stones.
So the גמרא says,
where are we? פסולה אם לאו אין תחת מזוזה אחרת, pesulah im
lav ein takhat mezuzah akheret, כי תניא ההיא בפתח שבחורי הדלת. ki
tanya ha-hi b-fetakh she-be-khorei ha-delet. No,
we're not talking there about a normal doorframe, we're talking about a
door behind the door. What does this mean? So basically what it
means is you've got two doors at the corner, here I'm using
this as my visual aid, you've got two doors at the corner
of your of your room, okay? So you would so the problem
question is here is this thing considered a separate door? Because consider
if I'm walking into my room here and I open the door,
what's left is it gets this door, right, gets into the opening
of the other door. If I go into this door, this door
gets into the opening of that door. So to what degree do
I need two מזוזות here or just one מזוזה? mezuzah Is this
one big door or not? And part of the answer is, is
there a טפח tefakh that separates these two doors? I'll consider them
separate doors or not. So the גמרא'ס Gemara's saying when does it
say that if there's a טפח tefakh you need another מזוזה? mezuzah
We're not talking about one doorframe and how deep in you're getting,
what we're talking about is these two, you know, catty-corner doors, not
catty-corner,
whatever,
perpendicular, that was the word I was looking for. I was going
to say orthogonal, but I thought I knew there was a better
word.
Anyway, these two perpendicular doors.
Orthogonal means perpendicular.
I couldn't think of the word perpendicular.
Okay, anyway,
thank you, yeah, like that picture. Anyway, so here if there is
a so if there's one door maybe if it's a טפח tefakh
and it's still good, but if there's two doors, when does it
say that if it's a טפח tefakh you need another מזוזה? mezuzah
What it means is these two doors are separated from one another
by a טפח, tefakh, then they're separate doors and you need a
מזוזה mezuzah for each. And it's separate than if
you have two doorways in from one place because you're talking about
going from one room to the other, going from.
Exactly, this is unrelated to that question. Okay, let's just read one
more thing about this. So the גמרא says like this, okay, כי
תניא ההיא בפתח. ki tanya ha-hi b-fetakh. Okay, the גמרא says הא
בהדיא קתני. ha bahedya katani. Well,
that's explicitly the explanation. The end of the ברייתא, braitah, פתח שאחורי
הדלת, petach sheachorei hadelet,
the opening behind the door, אם יש שם טפח צריכה מזוזה אחרת,
im yesh sham tefach tzerichah mezuzah acheret, if there's a טפח tefach
between that and the other door you need a separate מזוזה. mezuzah
So you see that's a different law than the preceding thing about
the about the brick. Says the גמרא, ואם לאו אינו צריך מזוזה
אחרת. v'im lav eino tzarich mezuzah acheret. But says no, כיצד קתני.
keitzad katani. No, is the second part of the ברייתא braitah is
elaborating on the first. But again, the ברייתא braitah that says if
it's a טפח tefach you need another מזוזה mezuzah is not only
talking about how deep into the doorframe you're doing it, it might
be referring to a special case of these of these
perpendicular doors. One last הלכה. halacha. The גמרא says like this, תנא,
tana, we learned in the ברייתא, braita, העמיד למלבן של
קנים, he'emid l'malben shel kanim, so you erected for it a sort
of a frame of
of reeds, so your doorframe is now made out of reed. So
what do you do? חותך שפופרת ומניחה. chotech shefoferet u'menichah. So you
cut one reed open, according to רש"י or תוספות it would depend
whether the reeds are going horizontal or vertical. Let's assume the reeds
are going vertical, which makes the most sense anyway. You cut open
one reed and you stick your מזוזה mezuzah. into your now you
have a מזוזה mezuzah case that's part of your door. Okay, so
you cut into a reed and you put your מזוזה mezuzah, into
it. Okay, that's fine, that's not a חידוש. chidush. But now it
goes on, it says אמר
רב אחא בריה דרבא, amar Rav Achah breih de'Rava, לא שנו אלא
שהעמידו ובסוף חתכו. lo shanu ela she'he'emido u'vasof chatcho. That's first you
erected your doorframe and then you you cut this opening in and
you stuck in your מזוזה. mezuzah ובסוף חתכו ומניחו, u'vasof chatcho u'menicho,
אבל חתך והניח, aval chatach v'heniach, if first you you stuck your
מזוזה mezuzah, in you you made your hole and you put your
מזוזה mezuzah in and then you put up your doorframe. So you've
got your מזוזה in your doorframe before you've erected your
doorframe. חתך והניח ובסוף העמידו, chatach v'heniach u'vasof he'emido, פסולה, that's invalid.
תעשה ולא מן העשוי. ta'aseh v'lo min he'asui. That's an הלכתי halachic
principle which is that you have to do something in the right
form. So you put your מזוזה in your doorframe, you do not
have your doorframe go up and and then automatically your מזוזה is
already there. Your doorframe now has to exist and your מזוזה has
to be made on it and not and not that it happens
like that. Now it's interesting that the phrase תעשה, ta'aseh, as Michael
says, is learned from סוכות. Sukkot. Sometimes the תורה explicitly says you
shall do, like חג הסוכות תעשה לך. Chag HaSukkot ta'aseh lecha. So
we learned that you have to make a סוכה, sukkah, it can't
be made automatically. For example, if somebody digs a hole in a
haystack and automatically now there's a roof, you didn't actually make the
roof, that's no good. The interesting thing is, so the principle is
the same, but the תורה does not say תעשה ta'aseh by מזוזה.
By מזוזה the verb always is וכתבתם על מזוזות ביתך. u'chtavtam al
mezuzot beitecha. But nevertheless the גמרא is using this as the principle
that the way you would say it reflecting the פסוק pasuk is,
write it on the מזוזה, the מזוזה would have to be there
and then it would have to be put in the מזוזה, not
that you erect the מזוזה and it's already there. But it uses
this phrase of תעשה ולא מן העשוי, ta'aseh v'lo min he'asui, which
is this generic הלכתי halachic phrase of saying you do you have
to do it, not that it becomes done automatically. All
right.